Helsby, Robert D.; Papers apap086
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Robert D. Helsby Papers
1966-1987
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Helsby, Robert D.
apap086
0.4 cubic ft.
The Robert D. Helsby Papers include materials that document his work as first chair of the New York State Public Employment Relations Board from 1967-1977 and include publications on labor relations, New York's Taylor Law and collective bargaining.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, before 1999.
Biographical History
Robert D. Helsby was born on August 2, 1918 in Denton, Maryland. His parents were George L. and Jennie Blanche Davis Helsby. He graduated from Gloversville (New York) High School in 1934, earned his BS from the State University College at Oswego in 1936, and earned an MA from the Ohio State University in 1948. He earned his EdD. from Cornell University's School of Industrial and Labor Relations in 1958 and did additional graduate work at Penn State University and Indiana University. During World War II, he served as a captain in the US Navy. He was a Commanding Officer aboard PT boats and on the staff of the Commander of the Armed Service Forces of the Atlantic Fleet in the Solomon Islands, New Guinea, and Philippine Islands. He married Colene Fay Arney Helsby in 1945 and had five children.
Helsby was the Executive Deputy Industrial Commissioner of the New York State Department of Labor and Executive Dean for Continuing Education at the State University of New York. He served as the first chair of the New York State Public Employment Relations Board from 1967-1977. Governor Nelson Rockefeller appointed the board and other members included George H. Fowler, Joseph R. Crowley, and Jerome Lefkowitz. From 1977-1981 he was Director of the Public Employment Relations Services, a Carnegie Corporation of New York project to assist public employment labor relations boards and commissions throughout the United States. In 1981 he became a professor of Industrial Relations at the University of North Florida in Jacksonville. He researched and published materials on labor relations, collective bargaining, and New York's Taylor Law. The Taylor Law was a result of the Governor's Committee on Public Employee Relations Report issued in 1966 and named after the committee's chair, George W. Taylor.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Robert D. Helsby include writings on labor relations, New York's Taylor Law and collective bargaining, and materials produced by New York's Public Employment Relations Board and its members such as Deputy Chair Jerome Lefkowitz. There are also news clippings and photographs from Helsby's tenure as chair of the Public Employment Relations Board. The collection also includes reports and documents produced by the State of New York about the Public Employment Relations Board and the Taylor Law.
The collection does not include any of Helsby's personal papers. For related collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives consult the Labor and Public Servants and Politicians pages of the Archives of Public Affairs and Policy.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Public Servants; Labor; New York (State). Public Employment Relations Board; Collective bargaining; Industrial relations; New York (State). Public Employees' Fair Employment Law; Albany (N.Y.); Publications; Newspaper clippings; Conference reports; Pamphlets; Reports; Articles; Books; Photographs; Helsby, Robert D.
- Public Employment Relations Board, 1966-1969; 1972-1976; 1978-1980; 1; 0.2 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes reports published by the Public Employment Relations Board and its members. It also includes material related to New York's Taylor Law and New York State government publications.
  - Governor's Committee on Public Employee Relations, Reports, 1966; 1968-1969 (Box 1 (1-Public Employment Relations Board), Folder 1)
  - The Joint Legislative Committee on the Taylor Law, Report, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Public Employment Relations Board), Folder 2)
  - "The Legal Basis of Employee Relations of New York State Employees," by Jerome Lefkowitz, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Public Employment Relations Board), Folder 3)
  - Public Employment Relations Board, Appreciation Dinner, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Public Employment Relations Board), Folder 4)
  - Public Employment Relations Board, Conference, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Public Employment Relations Board), Folder 5)
  - Public Employment Relations Board, News Clippings, 1967-1968; 1975 (Box 1 (1-Public Employment Relations Board), Folder 6)
  - Public Employment Relations Board, Photographs, 1967 (Box 1 (1-Public Employment Relations Board), Folder 7)
  - Taylor Law, Reports, Pamphlets, Reprints, 1967-1969; 1974; 1976; 1978-1980 (Box 1 (1-Public Employment Relations Board), Folder 8)
- Writings, 1977; 1979; 1985; 1987; 2; 0.2 cubic ft.
  Series two includes published and typescripts of articles, books, and reports written or edited by Helsby and others about labor relations and collective bargaining.
  - "Collective Bargaining in Education-Saint or Sinner?" by Robert D. Helsby, 1979 (Box 1 (Continued) (2- Writings), Folder 9)
  - "Compulsory Interest Arbitration in New York State-Experience Under the 1977 Amendments," by Robert E. Doherty and Mary E. Gallo, 1972 (Box 1 (2- Writings), Folder 10)
  - "Development of Professional Personnel for Public Employment Labor Relations Boards and Commissions in State and Local Governments of the United States: A Feasibility Study," by Robert D. Helsby, 1977 (Box 1 (2- Writings), Folder 11)
  - "The Evolving Process-Collective Negotiations in Public Employment," Robert D. Helsby, Jeffrey Tener and Jerome Lefkowitz editors, 1985 (Box 1 (2- Writings), Folder 12)
  - "A Practitioner's View: Reactions and Commentary on Dr. George W. Angell's Essay on Higher Education and Collective Bargaining," by Robert D. Helsby, Undated (Box 1 (2- Writings), Folder 13)
  - ."The Public Employment Dispute Resolution Process of Public Law 447 in the State of Florida: An Analysis of the Views of Labor Relations Practitioners with Emphasis on the Special Master Process," by Robert D. Helsby, Kenneth Jennings, David G. Moore, Steven K. Paulson, Steven A. Williamson, 1987 (Box 1 (2- Writings), Folder 14)